Finding Aid for the Albert and Elaine Atwood Collection on Thilo Becker and Otie Chew PASC-M.0060
UCLA Library Special Collections
Albert and Elaine Atwood collection on Thilo Becker and Otie Chew
circa 1888-1984
UCLA Library Special Collections
PASC-M.0060
2 Linear Feet (4 flat boxes, 1 document box)
The collection consists of material relating to the careers of Thilo Becker and Otie Chew, prominent Los Angeles musicians and music teachers. There are clippings and programs relating to their performance and teaching careers, and to the performance careers of several of their students. There are also scrapbooks documenting piano concerts given in Los Angeles from 1915-1956.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 994622603606533
Biography/History
Thilo Becker and Otie Chew were a married couple who were prominent musicians and music teachers in Los Angeles throughout the first half of the twentieth century. Becker, a pianist, was born in Australia in 1868, and spent several years studying in Leipzig, Germany before emigrating to Los Angeles in 1894. He gave a few recitals, but quickly gained more prominence as a teacher than as a performer. Chew, a violinist, was born in London in 1880 and was recognized as a child prodigy, earning a scholarship to the Royal College of Music at the age of 11. In 1907 she moved to Los Angeles and met Becker, and the two soon married. They enjoyed a prominent place in Los Angeles musical society, teaching scores of students and hosting guests at their home studio on Alvarado Street. In the 1930s they revived their performing careers for some time, giving a number of dual recitals in the city. Thilo Becker died on December 16, 1944 and Otie Chew Becker died on January 22, 1953.
Albert and Elaine Atwood were friends of Otie Chew. Elaine was Chew's youngest pupil, but they did not have a social relationship until Becker's death in 1944. As a widow, Chew became a close friend to both the Atwoods, traveling with them on many occasions and entrusting them with portions of her estate.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of material relating to the careers of Thilo Becker and Otie Chew, and to the careers of their students. There are clippings and programs, mostly contained in scrapbooks. There is an unpublished book manuscript by Becker and a small amount of music composed by him. There is a small amount of material regarding Richard Wagner, including cards depicting scenes from his operas. Also of interest are scrapbooks compiled by Marjorie Barker, a student of Becker's, that document a large number of piano concerts given in Los Angeles over the course of decades.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series 1. Personal papers
Series 2. Scrapbooks
Series 3. Music manuscripts
Musicians -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Becker, Thilo; Chew, Otie
- Series 1. Personal papers
  Scope and Content
  This series consists primarily of material relating to the careers of pianist Thilo Becker and his wife, violinist Otie Chew.
  - Biographical information for Thilo Becker and Otie Chew, 1895-ca. 1984 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes photocopies of Chew's certificate of admission to Windsor Castle; typed anecdotes related by Albert Atwood.
  - Book manuscript, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    "Thoughts Relating Principally to Music" by Thilo Becker [includes copy of telegram from Ignace Paderewski].
  - Cards - Richard Wagner, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Twelve cards depicting scenes from Wagner operas; post card for Parsifal.
  - Correspondence, 1891-1944 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Includes letters from Otie Chew to her parents; copy of a cable from Ignace Paderewski to Thilo Becker.
  - Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Contains program for world tour by Shibley Boyes [two copies, one inscribed by Boyes].
  - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Includes portrait of Richard Wagner; photos of Paloma Schramm and Shibley Boyes.
  - Photographs - Otie Chew, 1895 and undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photographs - Thilo Becker, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Photographs - Thilo Becker and Otie Chew, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Programs, 1890-1951 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Contains programs for performances by Otie Chew, Thilo Becker, Paloma Schramm, and Olga Steeb; program for memorial service of Los Angeles Times music critic Isabel Morse Jones.
  - Clippings, 1888-1953 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Journals of C.F.W. Schramm, 1897-1899 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Series 2. Scrapbooks, 1915-1956
  - Scrapbook, 1915-1951 (Box 1)
    Contains clippings and programs regarding piano concerts in the Los Angeles area, compiled by Marjorie Barker. [unbound]
  - Scrapbook, 1923-1956 (Box 2)
    Contains clippings and programs regarding piano concerts in the Los Angeles area, compiled by Marjorie Baker. [unbound]
  - Scrapbook, 1933-1937 (Box 3)
    Contains clippings and programs regarding Thilo Becker and Otie Chew.
  - Scrapbook, 1922-1955 (Box 4)
    Contains clippings and programs regarding the students of Thilo Becker [unbound]
  - Photocopies, 1915-1949 (Box 4)
    Contains photocopies of various pages from the scrapbooks in the collection.
- Series 3. Music manuscripts
  Contains handwritten music manuscripts.
  - Caruthers Conway compositions, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
  - Im Walde et. al. [Friedrich von Bodenstedt and others], 1903 (Box 3)
  - Paloma Schramm compositions, 1904 (Box 3)
  - Thilo Becker compositions [some cowritten with Paloma Schramm-Baruch], undated (Box 3)